I've just finished recording a video about
noon Cookie Monster ice cream whilst I'm
eating the rest of it let's talk about
dextrose in our sugar series episode 2.
Sugar and ice cream is essential, if you don't
have it your ice cream will be an absolute block
of ice that's just a fact. The sugar reduces the
freezing point of your mixture so that it turns
into ice cream rather than ice. So we discussed
basic sucrose in the first episode of our sugar
series and the second episode is dextrose.
So what is dextrose? dextrose is a simple
sugar made from corn or wheat, in North America
it's often called corn sugar in the UK it's
often called Brewers sugar and you can buy
it from any beer making or Brewing Company
out there pretty much all across the world.
Dextrose is almost identical to glucose and it
is actually a different name for D-glucose there
are two different types of dextrose monohydrate
and anhydrous, monohydrate dextrose has one
crystallized water molecule and anhydrous has
zero crystallized water molecules. Dextrose is
also used in energy bars because it's a simple
sugar your body can convert that into energy
very very quickly for that reason people have
often used dextrose to combat the effects of
diabetes or hypoglycemia which is chronically
low blood sugar when your blood sugar level
gets too low, you can buy dextrose tablets and
dextrose gel to rapidly increase your blood sugar
level to get you back to where you need to be.
In ice cream, dextrose is a lovely sugar to
include because it has such a high impact on
the freezing point this means that if you
change some of your sucros to dextrose,
your ice cream will be softer straight out the
freezer and easier to scoop. Also dextrose is
70 to 80% the sweetness of sucrose (table sugar)
so if you if you love your ice cream and you love
the texture but it's still too sweet to taste,
you can remove 20-25% of your sucrose and change
that for dextrose and you will keep the same
texture and drop the perceived sweetness level
down. With a POD of 70 and a PAC of around 190 it
affects the freezing point almost twice as much as
sucrose whilst reducing the perceived sweetness.
In ice cream you can use up to 50% dextrose and
still keep a recipe balanced this means that
if you love chocolate ice cream which always
goes hard when you freeze it, you can increase the
amount of dextrose, reduce the amount of sucrose
and your chocolate ice cream becomes much softer
and easier to scoop straight out the freezer. A
good place to start if you're just starting
with Dextrose is to use 75% sucrose or table
sugar and 25% dextrose, after that point
you can adjust to a level that suits you.
Nice and easy one for dextrose, again it's a
really easy simple sugar to include and has such
an effect on the ice cream I strongly recommend
you try it if you can get it if you can't get
dextrose sub it straight for glucose, it's
basically the same thing, you can buy powdered
glucose, liquid or glucose syrup all these kind
of options so if you find glucose syrup in your
Supermarket, you can use that in exactly the same
numbers as any dextrose amount in my recipes.
Hope you enjoyed a quick touch on sugars episode
2 and in a few weeks we'll do the next episode
so that you can understand a bit more about the
science that goes into making ice cream. Anyway
thanks for watching don't forget to like
and subscribe and I'll see you next time.